<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rod Machen</title>
    <description>Rod Machen&#39;s writings.
</description>
    <link>http://rodmachen.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://rodmachen.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2015 16:58:55 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2015 16:58:55 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>SXSW: Peace Officer</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The documentary Peace Officer has an agenda. It meticulously demonstrates the militarization of police that has increased over the last 40 years. If it was only that, it would be nothing more than an effective piece of propaganda. But then there’s Dub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William “Dub” Lawrence is the centerpiece of this tale, and it’s hard to imagine a better one. His smile is infectious, and his knowledge of the subject matter is vast. More than anything, though, it’s his story that shines through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2008, Dub witnessed a tragedy: His son-in-law was involved in an armed standoff with police that resulted in his death. The kicker here is that Dub is a former sheriff who founded his county’s first SWAT unit in 1975. That same group had now killed one of his family members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peace Officer details not only that case but others in Dub’s home state of Utah. Fortunately, Dub just happens to be an expert on re-creating crime scenes, and the walk-throughs of these events are fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several national experts are brought in as well to connect the dots from race riots to the war on drugs to SWAT teams serving warrants, and the end result is clear. Peace Officer makes a convincing case for a radical re-examination of the way force is used by police, and does so in a remarkable and compelling fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Originally published by the Austin Chronicle on March 19, 2015 under the title &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.austinchronicle.com/daily/screens/2015-03-19/sxsw-film-review-peace-officer/&quot;&gt;SXSW Film Review: Peace Officer&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://rodmachen.com/writing/peace-officer</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodmachen.com/writing/peace-officer</guid>
        
        <category>published</category>
        
        <category>screens</category>
        
        <category>sxsw</category>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>SXSW: The Grief of Others</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The death of a child is tragic beyond measure. Hollywood has mined this territory before, often with maudlin results, but Patrick Wang’s adaptation of Leah Hager Cohen’s novel The Grief of Others takes a more measured approach and is much the better for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set in the Hudson River Valley, The Grief of Others explores one family in the wake of a tragedy such as this. John (Trevor St. John) and Ricky (Wendy Moniz) have tried to put it behind them, but things aren’t going smoothly. Their daughter Biscuit keeps acting out in increasingly dangerous ways, and son Paul has enough trouble as an overweight kid facing bullies at every turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film begins with the arrival of John’s other daughter Jess (Sonya Harum), who shows up out of the blue, pregnant and directionless. She’s welcomed in, for the most part, but struggles with the underlying tension that pervades this home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harum’s acting carries much of the film, even in the presence of seasoned vets Moniz and St. John. Her interactions with local nice guy Gordie provide many of the film’s most compelling scenes, and the story ultimately becomes hers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subject matter could lead to a depressing viewing experience. That’s not the case here, and while the plot stalls at times, it’s a beautiful film wrapped around a heartbreaking event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Originally published by the Austin Chronicle on March 18, 2015 under the title &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.austinchronicle.com/daily/screens/2015-03-18/sxsw-film-review-the-grief-of-others/&quot;&gt;SXSW Film Review: The Grief of Others&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://rodmachen.com/writing/the-grief-of-others</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodmachen.com/writing/the-grief-of-others</guid>
        
        <category>published</category>
        
        <category>screens</category>
        
        <category>sxsw</category>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>SXSW: Texas Shorts</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For a program based around a single geographic location, SXSW’s Texas Shorts is all over the map. Thematically speaking, that is. Filmmakers from the Lone Star State cover the gamut from silly to serious, from CGI animation to gritty street shots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James M. Johnston’s “Melville” is an exercise in defying expectations. The main character is not only a bearded, African-American coffee roaster in Ft. Worth who dresses like a hipster ranch hand, but also a formerly aspiring hip-hop stylist who uses his chosen art form to deal with a diagnosis of cancer. It’s the coolest Cow Town has ever looked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Darknet Delivery” takes us to Manhattan where a group of friends negotiates the hardships of adulthood, an Internet drug buy, and the difficulty of relationships. While it was successful in interweaving several topical issues, including radical libertarianism, it was hard to have much sympathy for the bad choices of the rich and not famous. Some flaccid acting and a contrived plot didn’t help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SXSW favorite Anna Margaret Hollyman (7 Chinese Brothers, Funny Bunny) stars in Allison Cook’s “Woman of the World,” providing some much-needed mothering in the Hollywood Hills. Andy Irvine and Mark Smoot’s “+ / -“ takes place before motherhood begins as a couple grapples with what to do about a possible unexpected pregnancy in the minutes before the results of pregnancy test are revealed. The “what if” hangs over the pair like a dark cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The darkness continues in “Carne Seca” from Jazmin Diaz. Two young brothers struggle to deal with their father’s abusiveness in rural Mexico. In “Squirrel,” a visual poem by Tomas Vengris, a mostly faceless teen narrates her descent into a sordid sexuality featuring Sixth St. as a backdrop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lighter side as well. Austin Tolin’s “Detective Calzone” is as silly as its title would indicate; think CSI meets Naked Gun. Joe Nicolosi’s “Star Cadets” brings absurdity into outer space as a couple of bro wingmen deal with boredom and pickles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The OceanMaker” by Lucas Martell stands out as the only animated piece on the card. A dystopic future bereft of hydration (imagine Waterworld in reverse) sees the survivors fight over who can harness water from the few clouds that remain. This unspoken work speaks volumes with its stunning visuals and fast-paced action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program ends with its most arresting piece. John Bryant’s “The Samaritans” was shot near Marfa and features a most scathing examination of religion gone horribly wrong. It is cringeworthy in multiple ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Originally published by the Austin Chronicle on March 17, 2015 under the title &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.austinchronicle.com/daily/screens/2015-03-17/sxsw-film-review-texas-shorts/&quot;&gt;SXSW Film Review: Texas Shorts&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://rodmachen.com/writing/texas-shorts</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodmachen.com/writing/texas-shorts</guid>
        
        <category>published</category>
        
        <category>screens</category>
        
        <category>sxsw</category>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>SXSW: KRISHA</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;KRISHA is a powerful, moving film that delves deeply into tough subject matter to create an unforgettable depiction of a family at its best and at its worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writer/director/co-star Trey Edward Shults used what he had on hand to create his first feature film (an expansion of his award-winning 2014 short film of the same name): his parents’ suburban Houston house, many of his own relatives, and most importantly, inspiration from family conflict that most people would rather forget than explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Krisha Fairchild (Shults’ aunt in real life) plays the eponymous main character, and lives up to her billing as a “walking disaster.” The film centers around the tumult of this one woman’s life and the effect it has had – and continues to have – on her loving but wary family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setting is Thanksgiving Day, replete with turkey, dressing, and football on TV. From the first moment, we know Krisha is the outcast, an absentee mother and sister who has come home to make things right after long struggles with her own demons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addiction produces so much hurt, and this film doesn’t back away from that. But there are good times, too, just as with any family. Veteran Texas actors Chris Doubek and Bill Wise provide some genuinely funny moments in this complex and rewarding narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some, watching a movie like this can be hard, but Shults does the audience the favor of attacking his story head on. His unflinching eye gives us a cathartic view of the very real pain that can exist in domestic life troubled by addiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Originally published by the Austin Chronicle on March 17, 2015 under the title &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.austinchronicle.com/daily/sxsw/2015-03-17/sxsw-film-review-krisha/&quot;&gt;SXSW Film Review: KRISHA&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://rodmachen.com/writing/krisha-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodmachen.com/writing/krisha-review</guid>
        
        <category>published</category>
        
        <category>screens</category>
        
        <category>sxsw</category>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Future of Breakfast</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As a part of SXSW’s new SouthBites schedule, the Building a Better Breakfast panel concerned itself with more than the first meal of the day. Nothing less than a wholesale change in the way we produce and eat our food was on the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Zimmern of Bizarre Foods and Travel Channel fame headlined the event and stated early on that he was optimistic about the direction food is headed. “I’m bullish on the future,” he said, making a call for every level of food production to work together, including corporations who have the resources to do some things the little guys can’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other end of the business spectrum is Hampton Foods. CEO Josh Tetrick was on hand to talk about his Silicon Valley startup which uses plant-based materials to replace egg protein in products like Just Mayo and Just Cookies. While his high-tech food products might intimidate some consumers, Tetrick believes he can succeed if he can get people to expand their horizons and look beyond the technology. “You can expand your brain about what better is,” he said, adding that affordability and convenience must rival those of traditional products. “Some things in food tech are kind of fucked up, and some things are awesome.” Tetrick obviously believes his products fall into the latter category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zimmern used Nathan Myhrvold’s upcoming (eventually) book on bread as an example of what could happen. For decades, the world of bread books has concerned itself with looking back to the past for inspiration. Myhrvold’s work approaches the the topic differently. “What’s bread going to look like moving forward not moving back?” he said, “and I think that’s a brilliant question to be asking about all of our food products: What are we going to do moving forward?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a panel discussing a variety of foods, one answer to this question is simple: Go eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Originally published by the Austin Chronicle on March 16, 2015 under the title &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.austinchronicle.com/daily/sxsw/2015-03-16/building-a-better-breakfast-at-southbites/&quot;&gt;Building a Better Breakfast at SouthBites&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://rodmachen.com/writing/future-of-breakfast</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodmachen.com/writing/future-of-breakfast</guid>
        
        <category>events</category>
        
        <category>food</category>
        
        <category>published</category>
        
        <category>sxsw</category>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>SXSW 2015</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The South by Southwest “Everything” festival officially kicks off tomorrow, but for many, it’s already here. SXSW badge and swag pick up started today, and for the edu-cated among us, it started Monday. Either way, the next ten days will be a flurry for anyone who steps into Austin’s downtown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My badge is firmly in hand along with those cool cloth bags that make going to the grocery story another opportunity for hipster cred. As I get ready to help cover the festival for the Austin Chronicle, I want to look back on my history with the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all started in 1998. Spring break brought me to Austin in search of a city to move to after an approaching graduation from Texas A&amp;amp;M. A high-school friend of mine was living here (in the apartments next to the Beverage Barn on Guadalupe) so I had a place to stay. That week introduced me to the Salt Lick and Little City coffee in addition to SXSW, so it was a win all around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the previous few months I had been reading the Chronicle which was brought in every week to Marooned, our lone independent record store in College Station. That got me prepped, and after reading about the film festival, I decided to give SXSW a shot. My then-girlfriend/now-wife and I drove down to the Dobie to take in a flick. The ticket sellers convinced me to shell out a whole $35 for a film pass that would get me into numerous films over the course of the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the next several years, the film pass was my entrée to SXSW. A couple of years I got a wristband for music, but film was always my thing. Every year I looked forward to the Chronicle’s publication of the schedule of films. Seeing that multicolored grid was the sweetest of anticipatory delights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, I increased my participation by volunteering for the photo crew. Shooting the interactive and edu festivals got me a badge, that most coveted of festival accoutrement. Moving from the pass line to the badge line only increased my enjoyment of the experience. When I got the opportunity to get a press badge through the Chronicle, it was a no brainer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While SXSW is certainly a polarizing event for locals, I’m firmly in the pro category. The traffic and nuisance are real, but I love seeing my mid-sized city transformed into the hot spot for hustling and bustling. For one week, it’s New York or LA. Or maybe both. Instead of flying somewhere to be in the thick of things, thousands of people come here instead. What’s not to like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if I can only find some place to park . . .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; --&gt;

&lt;!-- (Originally published by the Austin Chronicle on XXXXXX under the title [title](http).) --&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://rodmachen.com/writing/sxsw-2015-a-look-back</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodmachen.com/writing/sxsw-2015-a-look-back</guid>
        
        <category>austin</category>
        
        <category>events</category>
        
        <category>screens</category>
        
        <category>sxsw</category>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>You’re the Worst</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Stephen Falk’s You’re the Worst is a romantic comedy with bite and lots of bad behavior. The premise may be familiar – it’s about a guy and a girl negotiating a new relationship – but the execution is fresh, funny, and surprisingly frank about sex. After a critically acclaimed first season last summer, FX picked up the show for a second season. Falk will be in Austin Feb. 1 to talk about his work and the business of writing for television.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Austin Chronicle:&lt;/strong&gt; You’re the Worst has captured the imagination of many. How did you approach writing a dark comedy for television?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stephen Falk:&lt;/strong&gt; I tried to tap into things that interested me and not worry about possible reception. I had gone through a bit of letdown with an NBC show that I did called Next Caller, and this came out of having taken a big swing and missed. I, ironically or counterintuitively, wasn’t afraid anymore. I came out of that situation more determined than ever to just do what I wanted to do, tell the stories that I wanted to tell, and trust that I had a place in this business, that I had a voice that people would react to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AC:&lt;/strong&gt; Sitcoms have their tropes. How did you choose what to keep, such as the best friends, and what to mess with?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SF:&lt;/strong&gt; Tropes of genres are established for a reason. It’s quite helpful when you have two prospective romantic partners to have a sounding board for each of them. They don’t have to be a same-sex friend, but it’s what’s been done. For me it was good because then I got to have those best friends realize and rebel against the fact that they’re just sidekicks. While it’s helpful, it’s also completely unrealistic. Even though our show is heightened at times, I think we’re very cognizant of trying to make sure we’re representing stuff that people could actually do and things people could actually say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AC:&lt;/strong&gt; What’s the balance between making your characters “the worst” without making them too unlikable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SF:&lt;/strong&gt; If you come at it from a humanistic point of view and don’t judge your characters but rather draw them as deeply flawed human beings who are figuring things out, and make sure they’re operating under the truth for themselves, and you understand where their backstory is – if you approach that from an honest and well-meaning place, if you’re not just doing things to have them be dicks but rather do things to demonstrate their singular humanity, I think you can get away with a lot. However, you do have to be aware that there are certain things you just can’t do and be aware of what will turn off an audience in a way it would turn you off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AC:&lt;/strong&gt; In 2000 you won the Comedy Screenplay Competition at the Austin Film Festival. What did that do for you at that point in your career?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SF:&lt;/strong&gt; I think it gave me a little bit of extra confidence. It also helped legitimize me a bit. It’s hard for executives to find new talent. You need those gatekeepers, and screenplay competitions have become de facto gatekeepers. It gave executives more confidence that they weren’t going to be wasting an hour and a half reading my script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AC:&lt;/strong&gt; You’re coming back to Austin for a talk. What can people expect?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SF:&lt;/strong&gt; It’ll be partially anecdotes from the front lines. Hear what it’s like to be in a writer’s room. It’ll also be some practical advice for people who are trying to do this. I talk to people a lot about the craft of writing and things I’ve learned. And generally whatever people want to know, I’m willing to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Originally published by the Austin Chronicle on January 30, 2015 under the title &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.austinchronicle.com/screens/2015-01-30/do-your-worst/&quot;&gt;Do Your Worst&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://rodmachen.com/writing/youre-the-worst</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodmachen.com/writing/youre-the-worst</guid>
        
        <category>published</category>
        
        <category>screens</category>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mocktails</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This year’s hottest beverage trend doesn’t have a drop of whiskey, gin, or Scotch. It might fizz and bubble, but it doesn’t have Champagne. There’s complex sugars, but you won’t find rum hanging about. In fact, you won’t find any spirits at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, mocktails were an afterthought – geared toward people who can’t drink for some reason. “Non-alcoholic beverages have long been associated with pregnant patrons, the underage kid who is tagging along on Mom &amp;amp; Dad’s night out, or perhaps businessmen/women on a client meeting during lunch,” says Jessica Sanders, co-owner of craft cocktail haven Drink.Well. Add those in recovery and the strictly religious and teetotaling got a bad wrap. At least it didn’t seem to be very much fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But increasingly, even regular drinkers are choosing to have alcohol-free outings. “Maybe they tied one on a bit too hard the night prior, or they’re working toward a fitness goal, or they’re the designated driver for a group of friends,” Sanders says. “They shouldn’t be left out of the party completely just because they can’t be the life of it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sanders also notes that having alcohol in every drink limits the number of drinks one can consume over the course of an evening. Low- and no-alcohol options make available the expertise and skill of a good bartender even when one doesn’t want spirits involved. “It allows guests to experience the flavor point of view and creative voice of a bar in a really unique way that doesn’t rely on hard booze to tell that story,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, that story could use a little character development. Jason Stevens, director of bars, spirits, and beverage at Congress, says traditional mocktails were “often over-sweet, often made from gun soda and artificial syrup” – think Shirley Temples. Virgin versions of classic cocktails would lack necessary bite. A Bloody Mary without vodka is little more than V8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as cocktail culture has shifted away from “saccharine vehicles to get buzzed,” as Steven puts it, so too are they looking to add more sophisticated flavor profiles to mocktails. The bar master’s palate is becoming as important as the chef’s. “Now we’re finding a wide range of flavor and culinary expression in cocktails, and people who can’t or don’t drink still want to experience this,” Stevens says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non-alcoholic drinks can even be a replacement for wine (not to mention boring iced tea and soda). At El Naranjo, chef/owner Iliana de la Vega offers various aguas fresca (perhaps the original mocktail), including horchata and hibiscus-based tea agua de jamaica, giving diners plenty of options. “If you don’t feel like having a drink, it goes great with your meal,” she says. At Congress and sister restaurant Second Bar + Kitchen, there is a full zero-proof menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what goes into making a good mocktail? A lot of the same skills and ingredients that make up traditional cocktails are still used, but the lack of hard liquor has to be accounted for. “By taking the proof out of the drink, you have to work a little harder to gain complexity and depth of flavor, but it’s so doable,” Sanders says. One way to accomplish this is through something like a drinking vinegar or shrub. While that might seem a little extreme, a strong flavor is necessary if one is trying to replace something as strong as gin or vodka.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stevens has his own take on replacing the hard stuff. “I sometimes create house ingredients like charred barrel water or blackstrap tea to imitate a spirits flavor,” he says. “Spices, teas, vinegars, jams, and more all come into play to build structure and increase flavor.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sanders is a big fan of bitters, using it in small doses, much like a cook might use vanilla extract. While that wouldn’t create a true alcohol-free drink, it can work for people looking to stay away from the effects of alcohol. It won’t get you buzzed, but the flavor does the trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like with any mixed drink, taking care of the basics is key. “You have to have a sense of what you want the drink to taste like in the finished product and use high quality ingredients in the right proportions,” Sanders says. Ultimately, the end result has to be up to the standards of the other drinks being served at the bar, and that includes the way it looks. “A cocktail should be delicious,” Stevens says. “They should be beautiful vehicles.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stevens approaches this trend by delving deep into the past, exploring archives for neighborhood soda fountain recipes. It might be easy to dismiss soda shops as cultural relics where two teenagers would share a malt with two straws. But history isn’t an Archie comic. Old techniques can reveal some interesting ways of creating modern drinks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flavor aside, the thing non-drinkers really want is the same “buzz” that their drinking compatriots get. It’s what Stevens calls the “shared experience between you and the bartender.” Sanders agrees that her patrons should feel that they are special regardless of the alcohol content of a drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hand someone a well-crafted non-alcoholic beverage with a bouquet of fresh mint, a beautiful lemon swath, and some fresh berries, and bam, now they feel like they’re being pampered,” says Sanders, “and that’s what the job is all about at the end of the day.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Originally published by the Austin Chronicle on December 26, 2014 under the title &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.austinchronicle.com/food/2014-12-26/burden-of-proof/&quot;&gt;Burden of Proof&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://rodmachen.com/writing/mocktails</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodmachen.com/writing/mocktails</guid>
        
        <category>austin</category>
        
        <category>food</category>
        
        <category>published</category>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mental Illness in the Movies</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The unreliable narrator is a powerful tool in the hands of the right author, and when it comes to movies, nothing is more unreliable than a character with a mental illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Austin Film Festival hosted a panel Friday that explored the cinematic depiction of varying levels of sanity . John August (Big Fish), Richard Kelly (Donnie Darko), and Jim Uhls (Fight Club) are all writers who have dipped their toe in the crazy soup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kelly breaks the sanity spectrum down into two poles. Psychopathy involves a character who is a victimizer, taking advantage of others and showing an extreme lack of empathy. Schizophrenia, on the other hand, turns the character into the victim. It is the latter syndrome that makes for more sympathetic characters, while the former is great fodder for tales involving serial killers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When discussing sanity, the underlying questions all deal with the nature of reality. What is real in this story? And if mental illness is involved, can we ever really know for sure?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Big Fish, August had to address the issue of truth. While truth is theoretically singular, in the movie, each of the main characters had a different kind of truth they were dealing with. The father told tall tales that captured emotional truth, while the son wanted the literal truth, thinking that would get to the heart of the matter. The truth is a not a collection of facts, and the “lies” his father told contained the important elements of his history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That doesn’t mean it was easy. If a father lies about his past, can he be trusted when he says, “I love you son”? In the end, August believes that maybe untruth is better than nothing. After all, myths might not be real per se, but they provide an explanation that soothes our collective anxiety when faced with the unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fight Club deals with both ends of the sanity spectrum, as the schizophrenic main character invents a psychopath to break himself out of a sleepless, consumerist haze. Because this split personality isn’t revealed until the end, there are no veracity issues for the audience to deal with, only a retrospective realization of all that has come before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kelly is hesitant to place Donnie Darko in the category of movies dealing with mental illness. His depiction of a break with reality could be explained by things other than insanity, like time travel or a religious experience. As much as anything, it’s a coming of age story – to which Fight Club’s Uhls proclaimed, “Adolescence is a form of insanity.” It can certainly feel that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the unreality of Donnie Darko, Kelly wanted to peek behind the curtain of this type of character. “I want to get into the logical operating system behind the crazy,” he said. “The architecture of the insanity.” To Kelly, “life is a form of insanity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s required of an audience to participate in this type of storytelling? “You have to have faith that this story is going to take you on a journey that’s worthwhile,” Kelly said. He then asked the audience at  St. David’s, where the panel was being held, “Are we in a church right now?”
Crazy, man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Originally published by the Austin Chronicle on October 26, 2014 under the title &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.austinchronicle.com/daily/screens/2014-10-26/austin-film-festival-mental-illness-in-the-movies/&quot;&gt;Austin Film Festival: Mental Illness in the Movies&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://rodmachen.com/writing/mental-illness-in-movies</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodmachen.com/writing/mental-illness-in-movies</guid>
        
        <category>published</category>
        
        <category>screens</category>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Setting as a Character</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Some shows are memorable for certain characters. Others have insane plot twists. Some stick with us because of the setting, exposing us to worlds with depths and intensities that live on beyond the viewing itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three filmmakers gathered at the Austin Film Festival Friday to discuss the importance of this often-overlooked aspect of filmmaking. Noah Hawley (Fargo the series), Vera Blasi (Woman on Top), and Cary Fukunaga (True Detective, Sin Nombre) all have experience crafting real and complex worlds on screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fukunaga admits to being a bit of an addict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hi, my name’s Cary, and I have a problem with setting.” During pre-production for True Detective, he would often spend 12 hours a day scouting locations. Eventually, they gave him his own motorcycle so he could go on excursions by himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result was outstanding. Southern Louisiana became as much of a character in the show as Rust or Marty. This wasn’t the original plan as the screenplay was set in the Ozarks. By moving it several hundred miles to the south, the Bayou State’s petrochemical industry loomed large over the proceedings. How could it not, with oil rigs and smoke stacks occupying the background of many of the show’s sweeping shots?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Hawley, he knew well the location he would be exploring with his television adaptation of the Coen Brothers’ cult classic Fargo. The frigid environs of Minnesota saw Marge and company deal with violence and oddity in equal measure. The adaptation would be more of the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During auditions in Los Angeles, actresses would show up in parkas trying to show what cold looks like. This made Hawley laugh. During filming in freezing conditions, “You don’t have to act cold,” he said. “You put the characters in those locations, and it becomes real,” noting that several scenes were filmed in subzero weather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blasi’s Woman on Top traverses the globe from San Francisco to her native Brazil and uses food to paint a picture. During the writing phase, she would cook every meal in the movie as she was writing it. This not only let her get the details about timing and ingredients right, but also infused the end result with an authenticity that’s hard to replicate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we see is not always what we get, however. Hawley bemoaned the state of current moviemaking that is dictated by tax breaks and other incentives. “Toronto for New York or Vancouver for anywhere,” is the way he put it. For Fargo, they had to go north of the border to Calgary during filming. While the snow looked the same, the crew had to be especially careful not to let any mountains creep into fictional flatland Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes memorable locations are the result of happy accidents. For the unforgettable climax of True Detective, the stone grotto buried deep in the woods was the perfect place for the height of the action. In reality, it is an old antebellum fort that Fukunaga stumbled upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fukunaga calls it a pantheon, and that type of location has been the site of ritualistic cult activity over the ages. He acknowledges that the audience doesn’t have to pick up on this for the scene to be effective, but this attention to detail is certainly a part of his process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other times it’s the little things that matter most. The home of Pearl and Lester Nygaard is plastered from wall to wall with upbeat slogans and syrupy aphorisms. Their relationship doesn’t mirror this needlepoint positivity at all, as Pearl states early on in the series that she “married the wrong Nygaard.” Ouch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hawley describes Lester as “a beaten-down guy who’s surrounded by obnoxious optimism.” Inside this seemingly cheery home, much darkness takes place throughout the series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a good location can’t make up for bad acting or subpar direction, it can make the work even better than the sum of its parts. Places have meaning, and movies that take advantage of this are the better for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Originally published by the Austin Chronicle on October 24, 2014 under the title &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.austinchronicle.com/daily/screens/2014-10-25/austin-film-festival-setting-as-a-character/&quot;&gt;Austin Film Festival: Setting as a Character&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://rodmachen.com/writing/setting-as-character</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rodmachen.com/writing/setting-as-character</guid>
        
        <category>published</category>
        
        <category>screens</category>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
